Neil Sheehan map collection.
Geography & Map Division Library of Congress
Neil Sheehan map collection. 1964-1987
G8020 coll .S4 Sheehan
Sheehan, Neil
73 maps
6 folders
Geography & Map Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists of 72 maps, and the most unique among them is an annotated map of the Battle of Tan Canh that occurred during the U.S. drawdown from the war in 1972. The other items include a disbound atlas of South Vietnam; various maps of North and South Vietnam; and U.S. military maps of South Vietnam and Cambodia. The materials appear to have been used by Sheehan in preparation of his 1988 book, A Bright Shining Lie: John Paul Vann and America in Vietnam.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Sheehan, Neil.; Vann, John Paul.
Organizations
United States. Army Map Service.; United States. Army. Engineer Battalion, 29th.; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; United States. Defense Mapping Agency.
Subjects
Roads--Vietnam--Maps.
Places
Cambodia--Maps.; Indochina--Maps.; Kon Tum (Vietnam)--Maps.; Laos--Maps.; Thailand--Maps.; Vietnam, Southern--Maps.; Vietnam--Administrative and political divisions--Maps.; Vietnam--Maps.
Titles
Former title of the collection: Neil Sheehan papers; Former title of the collection: Vann-Sheehan Vietnam War collection
Provenance
This material with accession number 20,919 was transferred to the Geography and Map Division from the Manuscript Division in 1994.
Access and Restrictions
The Neil Sheehan map collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Geography & Map Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Cornelius Mahoney “Neil” Sheehan (1936- ) is a journalist best known for his reporting on the Pentagon Papers, a secret Department of Defense study of the U.S. involvement in Vietnam. Sheehan, when working as a reporter for The New York Times in 1971, obtained the classified documents from Daniel Ellsberg, a military analyst employed by the RAND Corporation. The papers revealed that the U.S. had secretly enlarged the scale of the Vietnam War with the bombings of nearby Cambodia and Laos, and coastal raids on North Vietnam, none of which were reported in the mainstream media. The government attempted to prosecute Ellsberg but the charges were later dropped. In 2011, the Pentagon Papers were declassified and publicly released.
Sheehan published other articles and books on the Vietnam War, including the 1988 book, A Bright Shining Lie: John Paul Vann and America in Vietnam. It won the Pulitzer Prize for General Nonfiction and the National Book Award for Nonfiction.
Date Event
1936 Born in Holyhoke, Mass.
1958 B.A., Harvard University.
1961 1962 Night editor, Asian bureau, United Press International, Tokyo, Japan.
1962 1964 Saigon bureau chief, United Press International, Saigon, South Vietnam.
1964 1965 Metropolitan desk and general assignment reporter, New York Times.
1965 Indonesia correspondent, New York Times, Djakarta, Indonesia.
1965 1966 Vietnam correspondent, New York Times, Saigon, South Vietnam.
1966 1968 Defense Department correspondent, New York Times, Washington, D.C., bureau.
1968 White House correspondent, New York Times, Washington, D.C., bureau.
1969 National security affairs correspondent, New York Times, Washington, D.C., bureau.
1971 Bantam Books published Sheehan's investigative work the Pentagon Papers; it was reissued as The Pentagon Papers as Published in the New York Times (New York: Quadrangle Books. 810 pp.).
1972 Published The Arnheiter Affair (New York: Random House). Began leave of absence from the New York Times to write a biography of John Paul Vann.
1975 Resigned from the New York Times.
1988 Published A Bright Shining Lie: John Paul Vann and America in Vietnam (New York: Random House) Received National Book Award.
1989 Awarded Pulitzer Prize.
1992 Published After the War Was Over: Hanoi and Saigon (New York: Random House).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized in five series
Series I Annotated battle maps
Series II Annotated map of Pleiku, South Vietnam
Series III Sheets from Atlas of Southeast Asia
Series IV Maps of North and South Vietnam
Series V U.S. military maps of South Vietnam and Cambodia
Container List
- Annotated maps (Folder 1-2)
  Two battle maps annotated in grease pencil.
  - Battle of Kontum 1972, 1:12,500 (Folder 1)
    Kontum base map
    Loai 909 Series
    Annotated with grease pencil
    The map was prepared for Neil Sheehan at the 23rd Division near Pleiku in 1972.
    Drawn by Col. R.M. Rhotenberry, a senior advisor to ARVN 23rd Division. Red lines represent North Vietnamese Army and black lines ARVN.
    Portion of text that accompanies map: "Sketch shows how close NVA attacking from above and below the town came to linking up and then being to wheel and overrun Division C.P."
  - Battle of Tan Canh 1972 (Folder 2)
    Military grid
    Portion of text that accompanies map: "Tan Canh, Battle of 1972. U.S. Army map give to me by Col. Phillip Kaplan, senior advisor to ARVN 22nd, showing ARVN and NVA dispositions and other events during the final phase of battle. Drawn while I interviewed him in Binh Dinh Province, where reorganized 22nd then stationed later in 1972. Interview was at Firebase Crystal."
- Annotated map of Pleiku, South Vietnam (Folder 3)
  One annotated map.
  - Pleiku Area
    Sparse annotations
- Sheets from Atlas of Southeast Asia (Folder 4)
  Consists of 24 maps and administrative atlas of South Vietnam from 1972 to 1987.
  - North Vietnam, scale 1:1,750,000
    Political map
    atlas
  - Indochina Ethnolinguistic Groups, atlas
  - Indochina Industry, Mining, and Electric Power, atlas
  - Cambodia, 1:1,740,000
  - Indochina Population, atlas
  - Indochina Vegetation, atlas
  - Indochina Agriculture, atlas
  - Indochina Airfields, atlas
  - Cambodia
  - Cambodia Rice-Growing Areas and Population, atlas
  - South Vietnam Communist Administrative Divisions and Military Regions April 1973, atlas
  - Laos, atlas
  - Laos, 1:1,750,000
  - Laos
    Includes Ethnic Groups
  - Thailand
    Central Intelligence Agency
    Economic, Vegetation, Ethnic Groups, Administrative and Population
  - South Vietnam Population and Administrative Divisions September 1972
  - Azimuthal Equidistant Projection Centered on Saigon
  - Ho Chi Minh City 1982, 1:20,000; Vietnamese, Russian, English
  - Hanoi 1983, Vietnamese, Russian, English
  - Hang Khon Vietnam, Airline Map that includes maps of Hanoi and Ho Chi Minh City
  - Ho Chi Minh, Vietnamese
  - Hanoi 1987, Vietnamese
  - South Vietnam North Sheet Major Road Network 1973
  - South Vietnam South Sheet Major Road Network 1973
- Maps of North and South Vietnam (Folder 5)
  Includes 14 maps of North and South Vietnam, including maps of Hanoi and Saigon published between 1964 and 1971.
  - South Vietnam Provincial Administrative Maps October 1969 1969
  - South Vietnam, 1:1,760,000; Central Intelligence Agency
  - Vietnam Demarcation Line and Demiliterized Zone, 1:75,000
  - Indochina Area, 1:1,000,000; International boundaries
  - Indochina Communist Logistics System " 1973, 1:2,500,000
  - Indochina with Universal Transverse Mercator Grid 1972, 1:1,750,000
  - Indochina Bathymetry and Areas Subject to Flooding 1970, 1:3,500,000
  - Saigon and Vicinity 1964, Downtown and street map
  - Indochina Surface Configuration 1970, 1:3,500,000
  - Indochina Administrative Divisions 1970, 1:3,500,000
  - Indochina Precipitation and Monsson Airflow 1970, 1:3,500,000
  - Hanoi Street Addresses 1971, 1:6,090; Preliminary edition
  - North Vietnam 1971, 1:1,750,000
  - North Vietnam 1965, 1:1,136,000
- U.S. military maps of South Vietnam and Cambodia (Folder 6)
  Consists of 33 maps of Laos, Cambodia, Thailand, South Vietnam, and Indochina as a whole from 1965 to 1972 published by U.S. Army Map service, U.S. Army, 29th Engineer Battalion, Central Intelligence Agency, and Defense Mapping Agency.
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Saigon, Vietnam; Cambodia
    Department of Defense
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,001
    Long Xuyen, Vietnam; Cambodia
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1967, 1:250,002
    Prey Veng, Cambodia
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,003
    Quan Long, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,004
    Phan-Thiet, Vietnam
  - Sa Dec 1965, 1:50,000
    Vietnam
    Army Corps of Engineers
  - Vung Liem 1965, 1:50,000
  - Truc Giang 1965, 1:50,000
  - Duc Hue 1965, 1:50,000
  - Tuyen Nhon 1965, 1:50,000
  - Tan An 1970, 1:50,000
  - Duch Hoa 1969, 1:50,000
  - Vinh Thanh 1965, 1:50,000
  - Phong My 1965, 1:50,000
  - My An 1965, 1:50,000
  - Moc Hoa 1970, 1:50,000
  - My Tho 1970, 1:50,000
  - Cao Lanh 1965, 1:50,000
  - Phong Phu 1969, 1:50,000
  - Can Tho 1969, 1:50,000
  - Khiem Ich 1969, 1:50,000
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    An Loc Vietnam; Cambodia
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Khanh Hung, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Da Nang (Tourane), Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Kontum, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Qui Nhon, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Nha Trang, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Hue, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Da Lat, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Nam Can, Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1972, 1:250,000
    Chaven, Cambodia
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1973, 1:250,000
    Virachey, Cambodia; Vietnam
  - Joint Operations Graphic (Ground) 1973, 1:250,000
    O Rang, Cambodia; Vietnam